Guide to the Moses Stuart Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Moses Stuart Papers
1802-1848
RG 294
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
The collection primarily documents Stuart's professional work as a Congregational minister (1806-1810) and professor at Andover Theological Seminary (1810-1848).
Biographical / Historical
Stuart was born in Wilton, Connecticut on March 26, 1780. He graduated from Yale College in 1799 and was ordained on March 5, 1806 after studying with President Timothy Dwight of Yale. Stuart was pastor of First Church, New Haven, CT from 1806 to 1810. He was Professor of Sacred Literature at Andover Theological Seminary from 1810 to 1848. He died in Andover, MA on January 4, 1852.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was given to Andover Theological Seminary by Sarah Stuart Robbins (daughter) in 1910 and Mary Stuart Anthony (granddaughter) in 1946. It was transferred from Andover Newton Theological School to the Yale Divinity Library in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection is arranged according to the order prescribed by Stuart in a manuscript dated April 1837, "Expression of my desire, as to the disposal of my Manuscripts, viz. Lectures, Sermons, Essays, etc., which are not published. [Also in regard to the repubublication of some of my works already published]."
In addition to the items described above, there is some correspondence related to an unsigned review of sermons on the atonement by James Murdock, Daniel Dana and Moses Stuart, which appeared in Christian Spectator, vol. 9, September 1, 1824. Provenance of this material is not known, although the lettets were discovered with the Edwards Amasa Park Papers. Also, there are four letters of the Stuart family, gift of Mary Stuart Anthony.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I. Notes, Lectures, Essays
Series II. Sermons
Series III. Correspondence
Existence and Location of Copies
5 reels of microfilm: negative 101-105; positive 118-122
- Notes, Lectures, Essays, Series I
  - Note from Stuart: "Expression of my desire, as to the disposal of my Manuscripts, viz. Lectures, Sermons, Essays, etc. which are not published. [Also in regard to the republication of some of my works already published]" (Box 1)
  - List of sermons (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Sacred Literature -- Old Testament: Lectures 1-11 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    For full listing of lecture titles, see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Lectures on Sacred Literature -- Old Testament: Lectures 12-45 (Box 2)
  - Lectures on Sacred Literature -- Old Testament: Lectures 46-55 (Box 3)
  - Lectures on Hermeneutics, 1-8 (Box 3)
    Lectures 5 and 8 missing in 1910
  - Lectures to the Advanced Class; Notes -- Exodus, Psalms, EzekieL, Revelation (Box 3)
  - Notes on some portions of Ecclesiastes (Box 3)
  - Notes on the book of Joel, etc. (Box 3)
  - Letter from James Seixas, with corrections for Prof. Stuart's Hebrew grammar (Box 4)
  - Hebrew extracts and translations (Box 4)
  - Notes on Introduction to the Gospels (Box 4)
  - Notes for an Introduction to the Epistle to the Ephesians, 1834 (Box 4)
  - Translation of Tittmann, De Synonymis in Novo Testamento, chapters 1-4 (Box 4)
  - Notes on Sacred Geography (Box 4)
  - Arabic Grammar (Box 4)
  - Syriac Grammar (Box 4)
  - Dissertation on the importance, the difficulties and the practibility of obtaining correct editions of classical books for the use of colleges and schools in the United States (Box 4)
  - Memoranda Pindarica (Box 4)
  - Notes on the Phaedo of Plato (Box 4)
  - Extracts in regard to logos (Box 4)
  - Extracts from Gerard's Description de l'Egypte (Box 4)
  - Lecture on slavery (abstract) (Box 4)
  - Essays on different aspects of the subject of original sin (Box 5)
  - Address to students, 1834 (Box 5)
  - Address to students, 1836 (Box 5)
  - Address before the Bible Class Society, 1829 (Box 5)
  - Oration on taking my degree, 1802 (Box 5)
  - Temperance pledge (Box 5)
- Sermons, Series II
  For full listing of exact dates and scriptural texts of sermons, see original finding, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Dated sermons, 1804 August - 1806 October (Box 5)
  - Dated sermons, 1806 November - 1817 November (Box 6)
  - Dated sermons, 1818 March - 1829 January (Box 7)
  - Dated sermons, 1829 February - 1839 December (Box 8)
  - Dated sermons, 1841 November - 1846 August (Box 9)
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Correspondence relating to Christian Spectator review of September 1, 1824, including to Elias Cornelius and from J. Mitchell (Box 9)
  - Family letters: Moses Stuart to Abigail Clark, 1805 (Box 9)
  - Family letters: George Anthony to Abigail Stuart; Austin Phelps, to George Anthony, 1855 (Box 9)